<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mohammed Khalilia on Mohammed Khalilia</title>
    <link>http://scimk.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mohammed Khalilia on Mohammed Khalilia</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Mohammed Khalilia</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>End-to-end Joint Entity Extraction and Negation Detection for Clinical Text</title>
      <link>http://scimk.com/publication/negation-detection/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scimk.com/publication/negation-detection/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving Hospital Mortality Prediction with Medical Named Entities and Multimodal Learning</title>
      <link>http://scimk.com/publication/predictive-model-mortality/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scimk.com/publication/predictive-model-mortality/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clinical text provides essential information to estimate the acuity of a patient during hospital stays in addition to structured clinical data. In this study, we explore how clinical text can complement a clinical predictive learning task. We leverage an internal medical natural language processing service to perform named entity extraction and negation detection on clinical notes and compose selected entities into a new text corpus to train document representations. We then propose a multimodal neural network to jointly train time series signals and unstructured clinical text representations to predict the in-hospital mortality risk for ICU patients. Our model outperforms the benchmark by 2% AUC.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Digital Slide Archive: A Software Platform for Management, Integration and Analysis of Histology for Cancer Research</title>
      <link>http://scimk.com/publication/dsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scimk.com/publication/dsa/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Patients at Risk of High Healthcare Utilization</title>
      <link>http://scimk.com/publication/risk-stratification/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scimk.com/publication/risk-stratification/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Objective. To develop a systematic and reproducible way to identify patients at increased risk for higher healthcare costs. Methods. Medical records were analyzed for 9,581 adults who were primary care patients in the University of Missouri Health System and who were enrolled in Medicare or Medicaid. Patients were categorized into one of four risk tiers as of October 1, 2013, and the four tiers were compared on demographic characteristics, number of healthcare episodes, and healthcare charges in the year before and the year after cohort formation. Results. The mean number of healthcare episodes and the sum of healthcare charges in the year following cohort formation were higher for patients in the higher-risk tiers. Conclusions. Retrospective information that is easily extracted from medical records can be used to create risk tiers that provide highly useful information about the prospective risk of healthcare utilization and costs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cloud-based predictive modeling for asthma readmission</title>
      <link>http://scimk.com/project/predictive-model-cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scimk.com/project/predictive-model-cloud/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The predictive modeling process is time consuming and requires clinical researchers to handle complex EHR data in restricted computational environments. To address this problem, we implemented a cloud-based predictive modeling system via a hybrid setup combining a secure private server with the Amazon Web Services (AWS) Elastic MapReduce platform. EHR data is preprocessed on a private server and the resulting event sequences are hosted on AWS. Based on user-specified configurations, an on-demand web service launches a cluster of Elastic Compute 2 (EC2) instances on AWS to perform feature selection and classification algorithms in a distributed fashion. Afterwards, the secure private server aggregates results and displays them via interactive visualizations. We tested the system on an asthma patient readmission task on a de-identified EHR dataset of 2,967 patients. We conduct a larger scale experiment on the CMS Linkable 2008-2010 Medicare Data Entrepreneurs’ Synthetic Public Use File dataset of 2 million patients, which achieves over 25-fold speedup than sequential execution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://scimk.com/img/predictive-model-cloud.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;predictive-model-fhir&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clustering patients using activity of daily living scores</title>
      <link>http://scimk.com/project/adl-clustering/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scimk.com/project/adl-clustering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Stratification is a valuable technique for providing an insight on the structure of the patient population based on some features such as Activity of Daily Living (ADL) scores. Grouping patients can play an important role in designing clinical trials or improving care delivery. In this paper, we present a method for stratifying patients based on their ADL scores. Every patient is represented by a time series consisting of ADL scores recorded over a period of up to two years. This approach relies on Dynamic Time Warping (DTW) technique to measure the similarity between two time series and then using Relational Self-Organizing Maps (RSOM) to discover patient clusters. The analysis was performed on a population of 6,000 patients. Six clusters were discovered: patients with high risk and steady ADL trajectory, low risk and steady trajectory, patients with sudden ADL score jumps, patients with declining ADL score and others with steady inclining trajectory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://scimk.com/img/adl-clustering.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;adl-clustering&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digital Slide Archive</title>
      <link>http://scimk.com/project/digital-slide-archive/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scimk.com/project/digital-slide-archive/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goal of the ”Advanced Development of an Open-source Platform for Web- based Integrative Digital Image Analysis in Cancer” is to develop open-source integrative technologies to facilitate analysis of data provided by the National Cancer Institute’s The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA). Some of my responsibilities include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing annotation capabilities that allow users to markup image data and share and retrieve their markups,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assisting in transforming the current Cancer Digital Slide Archive currently hosted at Emory to an open-source software platform that enables other in- vestigators and institutions to deploy cloud-based infrastructure to manage, share and analyze their own imaging archives,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Providing computational image analysis capabilities that enable users to characterize tissues and extract quantitative imaging biomarkers using image analysis algorithms,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing integrative analysis dashboard to enable users to explore the relationships between quantitative descriptions of image data and clinical or genetic variables.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dgutman/ADRCPathViewer&#34;&gt;Code at Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://scimk.com/img/digital-slide-archive.png&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;digital-slide-arhive&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epilepsy treatment recommendation</title>
      <link>http://scimk.com/project/treatment-recommendation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scimk.com/project/treatment-recommendation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The aim is to build a reliable prediction model for predicting the optimal treatment of an epilepsy patient. The model will rely on an individual patient’s past history, and predict the treatment most likely to achieve a positive outcome. We are working with longitudinal data and thus, define index dates for the patients. Data from before the index date serves as input available at decision time, while data from after that point in time allows us to extract outcome values and characterize the treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://scimk.com/img/treatment-recommendation.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;treatment-recommendation&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying care coordination</title>
      <link>http://scimk.com/project/care-coordination/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scimk.com/project/care-coordination/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This research identifies specific care coordination activities used by Aging In Place (AIP) nurse care coordinators and home healthcare nurses when coordinating care for older community dwelling adults and suggests a method to quantify care coordination. A care coordination ontology was built based on activities extracted from 11,038 notes labeled with the Omaha Case Management category. From the parsed narrative notes of every patient, we mapped the extracted activities to the ontology, from which we computed problem profiles and quantified care coordination for all patients. We compared two groups of patients: Aging in Place who received enhanced care coordination (n=217) and Home Healthcare (HHC) who received traditional care (n=691) using 128,135 narratives notes. Patients were tracked from the time they were admitted to AIP or HHC until they were discharged. We found that patients in AIP received a higher dose of care coordination than HHC in most Omaha problems, with larger doses being given in AIP than in HHC in all four Omaha categories. “Communicate” and “manage” activities are widely used in care coordination. That confirmed the expert hypothesis that nurse care coordinators spent most of their time communicating about their patients and managing problems. Overall, nurses performed care coordination in both AIP and HHC, but the aggregated dose across Omaha problems and categories is larger in AIP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://scimk.com/img/care-coordination.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;care-coordination&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing Aging in Place to Home Health Care: Impact of Nurse Care Coordination On Utilization and Costs</title>
      <link>http://scimk.com/publication/aip-vs-hhc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scimk.com/publication/aip-vs-hhc/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the chronically ill, care delivered in the home is a lifeline to the self-management of chronic conditions. Currently, 90% of Americans age 75 and older have at least one chronic medical condition, and 20% have five or more chronic illnesses (AARP, 2009). The cost of caring for people with five or more chronic illnesses is roughly 17 times higher than for those without chronic illness (Bodenheimer &amp;amp; Berry-Millett, 2009). The complexity of the health care system makes it nearly impossible for patients and families to understand how various services work together, identify what legitimate and feasible demands can be made of providers, and learn how to obtain medical information in a timely and efficient manner (Anderson &amp;amp; Horvath, 2004; Smith, Saunders, Stuckhardt, &amp;amp; McGinnis, 2012). Care coordination is increasingly seen as a way to help patients, families, or other support networks manage medical conditions, and social and psychological problems more effectively (Yang &amp;amp; Meiners, 2014). The impact of care coordination on utilization and cost outcomes in older adults living in the community and receiving long-term nurse care coordination through Aging in Place (AIP) or routine care through home health care (HHC) is reported.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clinical Predictive Modeling Development and Deploy- ment through FHIR Web Services</title>
      <link>http://scimk.com/publication/predictive-model-fhir/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scimk.com/publication/predictive-model-fhir/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clinical predictive modeling involves two challenging tasks: model development and model deployment. In this paper we demonstrate a software architecture for developing and deploying clinical predictive models using web services via the Health Level 7 (HL7) Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resources (FHIR) standard. The services enable model development using electronic health records (EHRs) stored in OMOP CDM databases and model deployment for scoring individual patients through FHIR resources. The MIMIC2 ICU dataset and a synthetic outpatient dataset were transformed into OMOP CDM databases for predictive model development. The resulting predictive models are deployed as FHIR resources, which receive requests of patient information, perform prediction against the deployed predictive model and respond with prediction scores. To assess the practicality of this approach we evaluated the response and prediction time of the FHIR modeling web services. We found the system to be reasonably fast with one second total response time per patient prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cloud-based Predictive Modeling System and its Application to Asthma Readmission Prediction</title>
      <link>http://scimk.com/publication/predictive-model-cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scimk.com/publication/predictive-model-cloud/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The predictive modeling process is time consuming and requires clinical researchers to handle complex electronic health record (EHR) data in restricted computational environments. To address this problem, we implemented a cloud-based predictive modeling system via a hybrid setup combining a secure private server with the Amazon Web Services (AWS) Elastic MapReduce platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EHR data is preprocessed on a private server and the resulting de-identified event sequences are hosted on AWS. Based on user-specified modeling configurations, an on-demand web service launches a cluster of Elastic Compute 2 (EC2) instances on AWS to perform feature selection and classification algorithms in a distributed fashion. Afterwards, the secure private server aggregates results and displays them via interactive visualization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tested the system on a pediatric asthma readmission task on a de-identified EHR dataset of 2,967 patients. We conduct a larger scale experiment on the CMS Linkable 2008–2010 Medicare Data Entrepreneurs’ Synthetic Public Use File dataset of 2 million patients, which achieves over 25-fold speedup compared to sequential execution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clinical predictive model deployment using FHIR web services</title>
      <link>http://scimk.com/project/predictive-modeling-fhir/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scimk.com/project/predictive-modeling-fhir/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Clinical predictive modeling involves two challenging tasks: model development and model deployment. In this paper we demonstrate a software architecture for developing and deploying clinical predictive models using web services via the Health Level 7 (HL7) Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resources (FHIR) standard. The services enable model development using electronic health records (EHRs) stored in OMOP CDM databases and model deployment for scoring individual patients through FHIR resources. The MIMIC2 ICU dataset and a synthetic outpatient dataset were transformed into OMOP CDM databases for predictive model development. The resulting predictive models are deployed as FHIR resources, which receive requests of patient information, perform prediction against the deployed predictive model and respond with prediction scores. To assess the practicality of this approach we evaluated the response and prediction time of the FHIR modeling web services. We found the system to be reasonably fast with one second total response time per patient prediction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://scimk.com/img/predictive-model-fhir.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;predictive-model-fhir&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relational Fuzzy Self-Organizing Maps for Cluster Visualization and Summarization</title>
      <link>http://scimk.com/publication/frsom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scimk.com/publication/frsom/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The notion of Best-Matching Unit (BMU) in the proposed Fuzzy Relational Self-Organizing (FRSOM) algorithm is replaced by a membership function where every neuron has a certain degree of matching to an input object. The FRSOM is an extension of the relational self-organizing map. In the proposed FRSOM we incorporate a monotonically increasing fuzzifier and a monotonically decreasing neighborhood kernel. Initially, FRSOM assigns winning neurons. However, as time progresses adjacent neurons begin communicating and sharing information about the stimulus received. The amount of information being shared at a given time is governed by the fuzzifier and the number of neurons sharing information is controlled by the neighborhood kernel. Additionally, in this paper we show that FRSOM is the relational dual of Fuzzy Batch SOM (FBSOM) followed by experimental results comparing both FBSOM and FRSOM on synthetic datasets. Then we will demonstrate the visualization and summarization capabilities of FRSOM on two real relational datasets, Gene Ontology and a patient data consisting of Activity of Daily Living score trajectories.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improvements to the relational fuzzy c-means clustering algorithm</title>
      <link>http://scimk.com/publication/improving-rfcm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scimk.com/publication/improving-rfcm/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relational fuzzy c-means (RFCM) is an algorithm for clustering objects represented in a pairwise dissimilarity values in a dissimilarity data matrix D. RFCM is dual to the fuzzy c-means (FCM) object data algorithm when D is a Euclidean matrix. When D is not Euclidean, RFCM can fail to execute if it encounters negative relational distances. To overcome this problem we can Euclideanize the relation D prior to clustering. There are different ways to Euclideanize D such as the β-spread transformation. In this article we compare five methods for Euclideanizing D   to View the MathML source. The quality of View the MathML source for our purpose is judged by the ability of RFCM to discover the apparent cluster structure of the objects underlying the data matrix D  . The subdominant ultrametric transformation is a clear winner, producing much better partitions of View the MathML source than the other four methods. This leads to a new algorithm which we call the improved RFCM (iRFCM).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
