<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Big Data on Mohammed Khalilia</title>
    <link>scimk.github.io/tags/big-data/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Big Data on Mohammed Khalilia</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Mohammed Khalilia</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="scimk.github.io/tags/big-data/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Digital Slide Archive</title>
      <link>scimk.github.io/project/digital-slide-archive/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>scimk.github.io/project/digital-slide-archive/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goal of the ”Advanced Development of an Open-source Platform for Web- based Integrative Digital Image Analysis in Cancer” is to develop open-source integrative technologies to facilitate analysis of data provided by the National Cancer Institute’s The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA). Some of my responsibilities include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing annotation capabilities that allow users to markup image data and share and retrieve their markups,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assisting in transforming the current Cancer Digital Slide Archive currently hosted at Emory to an open-source software platform that enables other in- vestigators and institutions to deploy cloud-based infrastructure to manage, share and analyze their own imaging archives,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Providing computational image analysis capabilities that enable users to characterize tissues and extract quantitative imaging biomarkers using image analysis algorithms,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developing integrative analysis dashboard to enable users to explore the relationships between quantitative descriptions of image data and clinical or genetic variables.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dgutman/ADRCPathViewer&#34;&gt;Code at Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;scimk.github.io/img/digital-slide-archive.png&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;digital-slide-arhive&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
