<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nursing Informatics on Mohammed Khalilia</title>
    <link>http://scimk.com/tags/nursing-informatics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Nursing Informatics on Mohammed Khalilia</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 Mohammed Khalilia</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://scimk.com/tags/nursing-informatics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Clustering patients using activity of daily living scores</title>
      <link>http://scimk.com/project/adl-clustering/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scimk.com/project/adl-clustering/</guid>
      <description>Stratification is a valuable technique for providing an insight on the structure of the patient population based on some features such as Activity of Daily Living (ADL) scores. Grouping patients can play an important role in designing clinical trials or improving care delivery. In this paper, we present a method for stratifying patients based on their ADL scores. Every patient is represented by a time series consisting of ADL scores recorded over a period of up to two years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying care coordination</title>
      <link>http://scimk.com/project/care-coordination/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://scimk.com/project/care-coordination/</guid>
      <description>This research identifies specific care coordination activities used by Aging In Place (AIP) nurse care coordinators and home healthcare nurses when coordinating care for older community dwelling adults and suggests a method to quantify care coordination. A care coordination ontology was built based on activities extracted from 11,038 notes labeled with the Omaha Case Management category. From the parsed narrative notes of every patient, we mapped the extracted activities to the ontology, from which we computed problem profiles and quantified care coordination for all patients.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>