<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications on Mohammed Khalilia</title>
    <link>scimk.com/publication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publications on Mohammed Khalilia</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Mohammed Khalilia</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="scimk.com/publication/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Digital Slide Archive: A Software Platform for Management, Integration and Analysis of Histology for Cancer Research</title>
      <link>scimk.com/publication/dsa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>scimk.com/publication/dsa/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Patients at Risk of High Healthcare Utilization</title>
      <link>scimk.com/publication/risk-stratification/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>scimk.com/publication/risk-stratification/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Objective. To develop a systematic and reproducible way to identify patients at increased risk for higher healthcare costs. Methods. Medical records were analyzed for 9,581 adults who were primary care patients in the University of Missouri Health System and who were enrolled in Medicare or Medicaid. Patients were categorized into one of four risk tiers as of October 1, 2013, and the four tiers were compared on demographic characteristics, number of healthcare episodes, and healthcare charges in the year before and the year after cohort formation. Results. The mean number of healthcare episodes and the sum of healthcare charges in the year following cohort formation were higher for patients in the higher-risk tiers. Conclusions. Retrospective information that is easily extracted from medical records can be used to create risk tiers that provide highly useful information about the prospective risk of healthcare utilization and costs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing Aging in Place to Home Health Care: Impact of Nurse Care Coordination On Utilization and Costs</title>
      <link>scimk.com/publication/aip-vs-hhc/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>scimk.com/publication/aip-vs-hhc/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the chronically ill, care delivered in the home is a lifeline to the self-management of chronic conditions. Currently, 90% of Americans age 75 and older have at least one chronic medical condition, and 20% have five or more chronic illnesses (AARP, 2009). The cost of caring for people with five or more chronic illnesses is roughly 17 times higher than for those without chronic illness (Bodenheimer &amp;amp; Berry-Millett, 2009). The complexity of the health care system makes it nearly impossible for patients and families to understand how various services work together, identify what legitimate and feasible demands can be made of providers, and learn how to obtain medical information in a timely and efficient manner (Anderson &amp;amp; Horvath, 2004; Smith, Saunders, Stuckhardt, &amp;amp; McGinnis, 2012). Care coordination is increasingly seen as a way to help patients, families, or other support networks manage medical conditions, and social and psychological problems more effectively (Yang &amp;amp; Meiners, 2014). The impact of care coordination on utilization and cost outcomes in older adults living in the community and receiving long-term nurse care coordination through Aging in Place (AIP) or routine care through home health care (HHC) is reported.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clinical Predictive Modeling Development and Deploy- ment through FHIR Web Services</title>
      <link>scimk.com/publication/predictive-model-fhir/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>scimk.com/publication/predictive-model-fhir/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clinical predictive modeling involves two challenging tasks: model development and model deployment. In this paper we demonstrate a software architecture for developing and deploying clinical predictive models using web services via the Health Level 7 (HL7) Fast Healthcare Interoperability Resources (FHIR) standard. The services enable model development using electronic health records (EHRs) stored in OMOP CDM databases and model deployment for scoring individual patients through FHIR resources. The MIMIC2 ICU dataset and a synthetic outpatient dataset were transformed into OMOP CDM databases for predictive model development. The resulting predictive models are deployed as FHIR resources, which receive requests of patient information, perform prediction against the deployed predictive model and respond with prediction scores. To assess the practicality of this approach we evaluated the response and prediction time of the FHIR modeling web services. We found the system to be reasonably fast with one second total response time per patient prediction.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cloud-based Predictive Modeling System and its Application to Asthma Readmission Prediction</title>
      <link>scimk.com/publication/predictive-model-cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>scimk.com/publication/predictive-model-cloud/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The predictive modeling process is time consuming and requires clinical researchers to handle complex electronic health record (EHR) data in restricted computational environments. To address this problem, we implemented a cloud-based predictive modeling system via a hybrid setup combining a secure private server with the Amazon Web Services (AWS) Elastic MapReduce platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EHR data is preprocessed on a private server and the resulting de-identified event sequences are hosted on AWS. Based on user-specified modeling configurations, an on-demand web service launches a cluster of Elastic Compute 2 (EC2) instances on AWS to perform feature selection and classification algorithms in a distributed fashion. Afterwards, the secure private server aggregates results and displays them via interactive visualization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tested the system on a pediatric asthma readmission task on a de-identified EHR dataset of 2,967 patients. We conduct a larger scale experiment on the CMS Linkable 2008–2010 Medicare Data Entrepreneurs’ Synthetic Public Use File dataset of 2 million patients, which achieves over 25-fold speedup compared to sequential execution.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Relational Fuzzy Self-Organizing Maps for Cluster Visualization and Summarization</title>
      <link>scimk.com/publication/frsom/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>scimk.com/publication/frsom/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The notion of Best-Matching Unit (BMU) in the proposed Fuzzy Relational Self-Organizing (FRSOM) algorithm is replaced by a membership function where every neuron has a certain degree of matching to an input object. The FRSOM is an extension of the relational self-organizing map. In the proposed FRSOM we incorporate a monotonically increasing fuzzifier and a monotonically decreasing neighborhood kernel. Initially, FRSOM assigns winning neurons. However, as time progresses adjacent neurons begin communicating and sharing information about the stimulus received. The amount of information being shared at a given time is governed by the fuzzifier and the number of neurons sharing information is controlled by the neighborhood kernel. Additionally, in this paper we show that FRSOM is the relational dual of Fuzzy Batch SOM (FBSOM) followed by experimental results comparing both FBSOM and FRSOM on synthetic datasets. Then we will demonstrate the visualization and summarization capabilities of FRSOM on two real relational datasets, Gene Ontology and a patient data consisting of Activity of Daily Living score trajectories.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improvements to the relational fuzzy c-means clustering algorithm</title>
      <link>scimk.com/publication/improving-rfcm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>scimk.com/publication/improving-rfcm/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Relational fuzzy c-means (RFCM) is an algorithm for clustering objects represented in a pairwise dissimilarity values in a dissimilarity data matrix D. RFCM is dual to the fuzzy c-means (FCM) object data algorithm when D is a Euclidean matrix. When D is not Euclidean, RFCM can fail to execute if it encounters negative relational distances. To overcome this problem we can Euclideanize the relation D prior to clustering. There are different ways to Euclideanize D such as the β-spread transformation. In this article we compare five methods for Euclideanizing D   to View the MathML source. The quality of View the MathML source for our purpose is judged by the ability of RFCM to discover the apparent cluster structure of the objects underlying the data matrix D  . The subdominant ultrametric transformation is a clear winner, producing much better partitions of View the MathML source than the other four methods. This leads to a new algorithm which we call the improved RFCM (iRFCM).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying care coordination using natural language processing and domain-specific ontology</title>
      <link>scimk.com/publication/care-coordination/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>scimk.com/publication/care-coordination/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;More detail can easily be written here using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Topology preservation in fuzzy self-organizing maps</title>
      <link>scimk.com/publication/som-topology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>scimk.com/publication/som-topology/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the important properties of SOM is its topology preservation of the input data. The topographic error is one of the techniques proposed to measure how well the continuity of the map is preserved. However, this topographic error is only applicable to the crisp SOM algorithms and cannot be adapted to the fuzzy SOM (FSOM) since FSOM does not assign a unique winning neuron to the input patterns. In this paper, we propose a new technique to measure the topology preservation of the FSOM algorithms. The new measure relies on the distribution of the membership values on the map. A low topographic error is achieved when neighboring neurons share similar or same membership values to a given input pattern.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fuzzy relational self-organizing maps</title>
      <link>scimk.com/publication/first-frsom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>scimk.com/publication/first-frsom/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper we propose a novel fuzzy relational self-organizing map algorithm (FRSOM) that can be used to map a set of n objects described by pairwise dissimilarity values to a two dimensional lattice structure. FRSOM generates a fuzzy membership matrix replacing the crisp best-matching unit matrix in the regular relational SOM (RSOM). We found that FRSOM discovers hard to find substructures in the data that present a challenge to the crisp relational SOM. Furthermore, we observed a triple relationship that seems to exist among the number of data points in the training data, map size and the fuzzifier m. We compare FRSOM and RSOM using several synthetic datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving disease prediction using ICD-9 ontological features</title>
      <link>scimk.com/publication/disease-prediction-ontology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>scimk.com/publication/disease-prediction-ontology/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disease prediction has become important in a variety of applications such as health insurance, tailored health communication and public health. Disease prediction is usually performed using publically available datasets such as HCUP, NHANES or MDS that were initially designed for health reporting or health cost evaluation but not for disease prediction. In these datasets, medical diagnoses are traditionally arranged in &amp;ldquo;diagnose-related groups&amp;rdquo; (DRGs). In this paper we compare the disease prediction based on crisp DRG features with the results obtained employing a new set of features that consist of the fuzzy membership of patient diagnoses in the DRG groups. The fuzzy membership features were computed using an ICD-9 ontological similarity approach. The prediction results obtained on a subset of 9,000 patients from the 2005 HCUP data representing three diseases (diabetes, atherosclerosis and hypertension) using two classifiers (random forest and SVM trained on 21,000 samples) show significant (about 10%) improvement as measured by the area under the ROC curve (AROC).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting disease risks from highly imbalanced data using random forest</title>
      <link>scimk.com/publication/disease-prediction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>scimk.com/publication/disease-prediction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;More detail can easily be written here using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
